{"tossups": [{"question": "A 2010 redesign of this item removed the initials \u201cVDB\u201d from its front for the second time. During World War Two, these items were subject to a discoloring redox reaction when the chemistry-unaware Henry Morgenthau [[mohr-GEHN-thow]] authorized the addition of zinc to them. As a result, one of the most valuable examples of these items is the 1944 \u201csteel wheat\u201d variety. Since 2010 these items display a shield reading \u201ce pluribus unum.\u201d For ten points, name these coins which show Abraham Lincoln on the front.", "answer": "U.S. <b><u>penny</u></b> (or <b><u>pennies</u></b>; prompt on \"coins\" until \u201ccoin\u201d is mentioned)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "During this campaign, a combined 25 American and British planes crashed, with 101 fatalities overall. Gail Halvorsen dropped candy to awaiting children during this prolonged campaign, becoming known as the \"Chocolate Flier.\" After the Deutsche [[DOY-chuh]] Mark was introduced, Soviet troops cut off road and rail access to supply an occupied city, immediately causing this event. For ten points, name this aerial campaign led by the United States to provide aid and supplies to the German capital.", "answer": "<b><u>Berlin Airlift</u></b> (accept <b><u>Operation Vittles</u></b>; prompt on nonspecific answers)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "According to Marco Polo, a ruler of this city was locked in his treasure room without food or water for neglecting to spend his gold on the city\u2019s defense. That ruler of this city, Al-Musta\u2019sim [[al-moo-stah-SEEM]], legendarily died after being rolled in a carpet and trampled to death by an invader\u2019s horses. Harun al-Rashid built a library in this city, which was destroyed in a 1258 siege by Hulagu [[hoo-LAH-goo]] Khan. For ten points, name this city which contained a \u201cHouse of Wisdom\u201d before becoming the capital of modern-day Iraq.", "answer": "<b><u>Baghdad</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Due to his money struggles, this philosopher was offered fifty years pay in advance by Catherine the Great to serve as her personal librarian. Pope Clement XIII [[the Thirteenth]] banned a compendium written by this man, citing its skepticism of Jesus' miracles. Alongside Jean d'Alembert [[dahl-ehm-BARE]], this man compiled a \"systematic dictionary of the sciences, arts, and crafts.\" The chief editor of the <em>Encyclop\u00e9die</em> [[ohn-see-cloh-PEH-dee]] was, for ten points, which French philosopher?", "answer": "Denis <b><u>Diderot</u></b> [[deh-NEE dih-deh-ROH]]", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "An early lyric by this group parodies the nativist views of Enoch Powell and demands that immigrants return to their \u201ccommonwealth homes.\u201d This group's members took an ill-fated trip to Rishikesh [[ree-shee-KESH]] for a guided meditation course with Maharishi Mahesh Yogi. A member of this group left that course early to film the documentary <em>Raga</em> about his sitar teacher, Ravi Shankar. For ten points, name this influential band of the British Invasion whose songs \u201cGet Back\u201d and \u201cNorwegian Wood\u201d were credited to John Lennon and Paul McCartney.", "answer": "The <b><u>Beatles</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "For use on this ship, Louis Casella manufactured a resilient version of a Six's thermometer. Charles W. Thomson supervised the team of naturalists aboard this vessel, whose equipment included over 181 miles of hemp rope. This vessel, commanded by George Nares and Frank Thomson, became the first to measure the depth of an area at the south end of the Mariana Trench. A four-year 1870s oceanographic expedition was undertaken by, for ten points, what Royal Navy vessel, after which the deepest point in the Marianas Trench was named?", "answer": "HMS <em><b><u>Challenger</u></b></em> (accept <b><u>Challenger</u></b> Deep[/a])", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "English physician Thomas Sydenham wrote a 17th century manual advocating for a product containing this good, laudanum. Soldiers from the Kuomintang organized what became the \"Golden Triangle\" for production of this good while operating in Laos, Thailand and Myanmar. European traders sold this good to circumvent the Canton system, which exclusively required silver be spent to acquire goods like tea and porcelain. The Qing [[CHING]] and British empires fought two wars named for, for ten points, what illicit drug later used to produce heroin?", "answer": "<b><u>Opium</u></b> poppy (accept <b><u>Opium</u></b> Wars; accept <b><u>Opium</u></b> Triangle; or <b><u>Opium</u></b> Crescent; prompt on \"Opiate\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Under these laws, a high concrete wall was used to divide off the Eight Mile-Wyoming Area. Ferris State University contains a memorabilia museum that houses artifacts related to these laws, which created a \"ghetto domestic sector.\" These laws were almost circumvented in the 1875 Civil Rights Act, which the Supreme Court ruled unconstitutional. Leading to \"colored\" restrooms being a norm, for ten points, what were these racial segregation laws in the Southern United States?", "answer": "<b><u>Jim Crow</u></b> Laws (prompt on \"Racial Segregation\" or \"Exclusion\" before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The deflection of this element\u2019s particles led to J. J. Thomson\u2019s discovery of atomic isotopes. It\u2019s not krypton, but British chemist Sir William Ramsay and Morris W. Travers isolated this element in 1898 and named it for the Greek word for \u201cNew.\u201d As a byproduct of air liquefaction, this element was shown by Georges Claude to be able to produce light in sealed tubes. For ten points, name this element historically used for signs in Las Vegas.", "answer": "<b><u>Neon</u></b> (accept <b><u>Ne</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "Science - Chemistry"}, {"question": "At the behest of Eugene Reybold, a project focused on this river employed a number of Camp Clinton-housed prisoners from the German Afrika Korps. A series of levees were built along this river in the aftermath of an event that bolstered Huey Long\u2019s gubernatorial campaign and resulted in Herbert Hoover leading a series of relief operations. That piece of legislation also mandated the creation of the Birds Point-New Madrid Floodway along this river. For ten points, name this major American river that experienced a \u201cgreat\u201d 1927 flood.", "answer": "<b><u>Mississippi</u></b> River", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Working with General David Canaberro, this general established the Juliana Republic in southern Brazil. This man was infuriated by an agreement made at Plombi\u00e8res [[plohm-BEE-air]], which promised to cede his home city of Nice to France. This leader of the \"Hunters of the Alps\" aligned with the Colorados during the Uruguayan Civil War, after which he returned to his home country to lead the Expedition of the Thousand to Sicily. For ten points, name this Italian general, considered a father of the First Italian Republic.", "answer": "Giuseppe <b><u>Garibaldi</u></b> (or Giuseppe Maria <b><u>Garibaldi</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The fanfare <em>Buckaroo Holiday</em> begins a ballet by this composer, whose choreographer, Agnes de Mille, later worked on the thematically similar <em>Oklahoma!</em>. Martha Graham earned a Pulitzer Prize for her work with this composer for a piece which celebrates the American pioneer and includes a reworking of the Shaker hymn \"Simple Gifts.\" <em>Rodeo</em>, <em>Fanfare for the</em> <em>Common Man</em>, and <em>Appalachian Spring</em> were written by, for ten points, which American composer?", "answer": "Aaron <b><u>Copland</u></b> [[KOHP-land]]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "For years, scholars suspected that several frescoes in the Hall of the Five Hundred at the Palazzo Vecchio were painted over this man's historical work, <em>The Battle of Anghiari</em>. Under the patronage of Ludovico Sforza, this man developed a design for a \"turtle-shell\" fighting vehicle as well as a self-propelled cart and an automaton, though most of his work went unpublished due to being written in a secretive mirror script. For ten points, name this painter and inventor who is considered the consummate \"Renaissance Man.\"", "answer": "<b><u>Leonardo</u><u>da Vinci</u></b> (accept either underlined portion)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "This acquisition was retroactively confirmed by the decision <em>American Insurance Co.</em> <em>v. Canter</em>. Secretary of the Treasury Albert Gallatin informed the sitting president that this acquisition was protected by the treaty-making provision in the Constitution. The costliness of the Haitian revolution led to this sale of territory by Napoleon to the United States. The Jefferson administration facilitated, for ten points, what \"Purchase\" which doubled the size of the United States?", "answer": "<b><u>Louisiana</u></b> Purchase", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "An invention produced by Andreas Flocken is often considered the first \"true\" one of these objects, which were also produced by Walter Bersey in London. The development of MOSFET helped spark the modern commercial interest in these objects, whose first mass-produced example was the Roadster. Initially eclipsed by the emergence of internal-combustion engine vehicles, for ten points, what are these vehicles run entirely without gasoline, including the popular Tesla Model 3?", "answer": "<b><u>Electric Car</u></b> (accept <b><u>Electric vehicle</u></b>; accept descriptive answers about <b><u>cars</u> </b>running on a lithium-ion <b><u>battery</u></b> or <b><u>cars</u></b> running on <b><u>electricity</u></b>; prompt on \"Car\")", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "Successful commanders from this kingdom were often equated to the god Montu, a war deity who takes the shape of a bull. This polity employed the <em>Medjay</em>, a distinct Cushitic speaking people who served as a paramilitary police force. This kingdom created the sickle shaped sword meant for close-combat known as the <em>Khopesh</em>, and its military mass-adopted the chariot after being invaded by the Hyksos [[HIK-sohs]]. For ten points, name this ancient African kingdom which fought at the Battles of Megiddo and the Nile Delta.", "answer": "Kingdom of <b><u>Egypt</u></b> (accept A<b><u>egypt</u></b>tos; accept <b><u>Kemet</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "A tyrant of this city named Dionysius the Elder arrested the philosopher Plato and sold him into slavery following a disagreement. A former general of Pyrrhus of Epirus, Hiero II, served as a tyrant of this city, becoming a client of Rome during the First Punic War. Archimedes allegedly used a parabolic reflector to defend this city from a Roman attack, inventing the first \"heat ray.\" For ten points, name this ancient Greek colony in the southeast of Sicily.", "answer": "<b><u>Syracuse</u></b> (accept <b><u>Syracusa</u></b>; or <b><u>Sarausa</u></b>; or <b><u>Syracusae</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "A subset of the \"Great Railroad Strike of 1877\" in this city included strikers trapping police officers on the Halsted Street bridge in the Battle of the Viaduct. During the \"Red Summer,\" this city suffered a race riot on its South Side after African-American teen Eugene Williams was killed for swimming near an \"All-White\" beach. This city's Hyde Park neighborhood hosted the Columbian Exposition of 1893. Hull House was founded in, for ten points, which Midwestern city that suffered a \"Great Fire\" in the 1870s?", "answer": "<b><u>Chicago</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>In 1937, this organization became the namesake of an orchestra conducted by</u></b> <b><u>Arturo Toscanini that transformed into the Symphony of the Air in 1954. This</u></b> <b><u>organization hired Peter Adler to conduct a namesake Opera Theatre that premiered</u></b> <em><b><u>Amahl and</u></b></em><b><u> (+)</u> </b><em><b>the Night Visitors</b></em><b> in 1951. Doc Severinsen, Max Weinberg, and Kevin Eubanks have led in-house bands on this company's late-night (*) </b>shows. For ten points, name this radio and TV network which trademarked the three-chime sequence that plays over its peacock logo.", "answer": "<b><u>NBC</u></b> (or <b><u>National Broadcasting Company</u></b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Misc Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>A</u> </b><em><b><u>tableau</u></b></em><b><u> by this artist depicts the historical Battle of Taillebourg [[TIE-bur]]</u></b> <b><u>during the Saintonge [[sahn-TAHNG]] War. While an attach\u00e9 to a diplomatic envoy to</u></b> <b><u>the Kingdom of (+)</u> Morocco, this artist painted the Orientalist work </b><em><b>Women of Algiers</b></em><b>. The toppling of Charles X [[the Tenth]] is represented by this artist in a painting depicting a bare-breasted women carrying the tricolour [[tree-koh-LOHR]] flag of France. </b><em><b>Liberty</b></em><b> (*) </b><em>Leading the People</em> was painted by, for ten points, which French Romantic artist?", "answer": "Eug\u00e8ne <b><u>Delacroix</u></b> (or Ferdinand Victor Eug\u00e8ne <b><u>Delacroix</u></b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>In the 2020 senate election in this U.S. state, a conspiracy theorist who claims</u></b> <b><u>to have invented e-mail, Shiva Ayyadurai, was defeated in the Republican primary. The</u></b> <b><u>kidnapping of Colin Bower's children and the police killing of DJ (+)</u> Henry became issues in this state's Democratic primary, which determined who would face Republican nominee Kevin O'Connor. A congressman from a political dynasty in this state lost the primary to incumbent Ed (*) </b>Markey. For ten points, name this state from which Markey continues to serve as senator alongside Elizabeth Warren.", "answer": "<b><u>Massachusetts</u></b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b><u>This non-Chinese figure trained at the Whampoa Military Academy and offered</u></b> <b><u>David Ben-Gurion and the Jewish people a homeland in his nation. This politician used</u></b> <b><u>the pseudonym \"Nguyen [[WHEN]] the (+)</u> Patriot\" while writing articles prior to the Versailles Peace Talks. This man led the 1945 August General Uprising which successfully deposed the colonial French following the nine-year First (*) </b>Indochina War. The city of Saigon was renamed in honor of, for ten points, which first president of communist Vietnam?", "answer": "Ho Chi <b><u>Minh</u></b> (or Nguy\u1ec5n Sinh <b><u>Cung</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In this man\u2019s final run for office, he defeated mayor Emory Folmar after</u></b> <b><u>narrowly winning the Democratic primary against Lieutenant Governor George</u></b> <b><u>McMillan. During one of his four runs for president, this man survived an assassination</u></b> <b><u>attempt which left him paralyzed (+)</u> below the waist. This man briefly served as First Gentleman after his wife, Lurleen, became (*) </b>Alabama\u2019s first female governor. For ten points, name this long-time Alabama politician who once declared \u201csegregation now, segregation tomorrow, segregation forever.\u201d", "answer": "George <b><u>Wallace</u></b> (accept George Corley <b><u>Wallace</u></b> Jr.)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Soe Naing was the first of over a hundred journalists from this nation to be</u></b> <b><u>imprisoned in 2021, with many being placed in the Insein Prison first run by the State</u></b> <b><u>Law and Order (+)</u> Restoration Council. 2020 election results in this nation were annulled following a coup by the Tatmadaw [[taht-MAH-\"tau\"]] armed forces. That coup removed Aung (*) </b>San Suu Kyi [[CHEE]] from power in, for ten points, which southeast Asian nation, once known as Burma?", "answer": "<b><u>Myanmar</u></b> (accept Republic of the Union of <b><u>Myanmar</u></b>; or Pyidaunzu Thanm\u0103da <b><u>My\u0103ma</u></b> Nainngandaw; accept <b><u>Burma</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man compared the extinction of civilization to that of a species in his 1910</u></b> <b><u>Romanes lecture</u> </b><em><b><u>Biological Analogies in History</u></b></em><b><u>. A late 1880s winter killed much of this</u></b> <b><u>man's cattle, forcing him to abandon his ranching venture at Elkhorn. With his son, (+)</u></b> <b>Kermit, this man headed a namesake expedition with the Smithsonian, collecting over 11,000 animal specimens and authoring </b><em><b>African Game Trails</b></em><b>. (*) </b>For ten points, name this U.S. president, whose saving of a cub led to the creation of his namesake stuffed bear.", "answer": "<b><u>T</u></b>heodore <b><u>Roosevelt</u></b> Jr. (or <b><u>T</u></b>eddy [a]Roosevelt; prompt on \"Roosevelt\" or \"T.R.\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Medieval historian Roger of Wendover claimed that this man offered to convert</u></b> <b><u>to Islam if Muhammad al-Nasir lent him military support. This man's refusal to appoint</u></b> <b><u>sub-prior Reginald to the post of Archbishop of (+)</u> Canterbury led to his temporary excommunication by Innocent III. This king was temporarily deposed by the French King, Louis the Lion, after he captured half of England during the First (*) </b>Barons' War.  For ten points, name this brother of Richard the Lionheart and signer of the <em>Magna Carta</em>.", "answer": "King <b><u>John</u></b> (accept <b><u>John</u></b> Lackland)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Muslim scholar Barani writes that \"not a dog and cat\" was left in this city after</u></b> <b><u>Muhammad bin Tughluq moved the seat of his government to the Deogiri citadel. A (+)</u></b> <b>sultan of this city named Ibrahim Lodi died on the battlefield at Panipat attempting to stop Babur the Tiger's invasion. The Kashmiri, Turkman and Lahori gates of this city all lead to this city's focal point, the (*) </b>Red Fort, which was built by Shah Jahan. For ten points, name this Indian city that was capital of a namesake sultanate and the Mughal Empire.", "answer": "<b><u>Delhi</u></b> (Accept New <b><u>Delhi</u></b> or Old <b><u>Delhi</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}